<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog</id>
    <title>Docs to connect the dots! Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-03-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Docs to connect the dots! Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/static/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mexico IT research]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/IT-market</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/IT-market"/>
        <updated>2024-03-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cómo es el estado de un mercado?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cómo es el estado de un mercado?</p>
<p>El conocimiento del estado requiere un estudio más táctico de las tendencias de oferta y demanda en un sector específico de una industria.</p>
<p>Cómo es el estado de un sector de la economía?</p>
<p>Este conocimiento requiere un estudio más estratégico de un sector específico de la actividad economica.
Puedo obtener información de una industria mediante metricas clave como marketsize, growth rate, profitability margins, technological innovation, regulatory compliance and industry concentration (market share of top players)</p>
<p>Qué estado está la industria/services en México?</p>
<p>Most important industries in Mexico is the automotive industry. Difference with other countries is that Mexico is not only an assembler, its industry also produces technologically complex components and engages in some research and development activities, an example of that is the new Volkswagen Jetta model with up to 70% of parts designed in Mexico.</p>
<p>An Original Equipment Manufacturer (<strong>OEM</strong>) makes components of another company's products. An OEM component might be a part, a subsystem, or software. Examples include operating systems (OS) and microprocessors in computers. Typically, the computer manufacturer makes neither the microprocessor nor the OS.</p>
<p>Engineering and design is also important in Mexico, driven by low cost of manufactering and desing in Mexico. Strategic position as major consumer of electornics market.
German multinational engineering and electronics conglomerate <em>Siemens</em> has a significant Mexican base.</p>
<p>From late 1990's , Mexico started to shift from simple line assembly work to more advanced work such as research, design, and the manufacture of advanced electronics systems such as LCD panels, semiconductors, microprocessors etc.</p>
<p>In the energy sector of Oil, Mexico has Pemex, actually the largest company in Mexico. It is still the most valuable company, nevertheless, its profit for the government (which taxes it for almost 62%) has been declining steadily over decades. In 1980, oil exports accounted for 61.6% of total exports; by 2010 it was only 7.3%. oil</p>
<p>Retail sector with FAMSA and Walmart is strong in Mexico.</p>
<p>A wave of acquisitions has left Mexico's financial sector in foreign hands. This has advantages such as increased competitive financial market leading to better financial services for the Mexican population but also drawbacks such as liquidity, capital flow and market stability problems in case of crisis of political and wars problems between countries.</p>
<p>Services are important (turism and financial services). Manufacturing is important. Oil is still important in Mexico's economy.</p>
<p>Qué puntos de referencia tiene para compararse en otros paises?
GDP growth for exogenous or internal factors. How technological advancements impact factors of production: labor, capital, entrepeneourship, land.</p>
<p>Mexico is a country of services:</p>
<ul>
<li>58.8% of GDP is for services (tertiary sector)</li>
<li>32.1% of GDP is for industry (secundary sector)</li>
<li>4.1% of GDP is for agriculture (primary sector)</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="yo-tengo-una-empresa-en-la-industria-produciendo-o-servicio-sirviendo-x-qué-quiero-de-un-colaboradorempleado-qué-busco-de-él">Yo tengo una empresa en la industria produciendo o servicio sirviendo X. Qué quiero de un colaborador/empleado, qué busco de él?<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/IT-market#yo-tengo-una-empresa-en-la-industria-produciendo-o-servicio-sirviendo-x-qu%C3%A9-quiero-de-un-colaboradorempleado-qu%C3%A9-busco-de-%C3%A9l" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Yo tengo una empresa en la industria produciendo o servicio sirviendo X. Qué quiero de un colaborador/empleado, qué busco de él?" title="Direct link to Yo tengo una empresa en la industria produciendo o servicio sirviendo X. Qué quiero de un colaborador/empleado, qué busco de él?">​</a></h3>
<p>Tengo tareas ambiguas sin dirección clara que necesitan ser realizadas, él puede realizarlas?</p>
<p>¿Cómo evaluo si él puede realizarlas?</p>
<p>Debo evaluar claramente por qué quiere trabajar en mi empresa.</p>
<p>A qué rol está aplicando para yo saber qué tipo de preguntas dirigir y entender su motivación e interes.</p>
<p>Si desarrollo un producto, entonces el debe ser eficiente en el desarrollo de ese producto.</p>
<p>Si doy un servicio, espero que conozca sobre el servicio y tenga las cualidades necesarias para mantener y mejorar la oferta de ese servicio.</p>
<p>Qué factores de confianza debo evaluar para decidir si hacer una oferta o no?</p>
<p>Si solo quiere dinero, se irá cuando le ofrezcan más dinero.
Si solo quiere aprender, se quedará en tanto el sienta que sigue aprendiendo.
Se quedará si tiene una fuerte convicción sobre lo que la empresa sirve o produce.</p>
<ol>
<li>Identifica 5 empresas de servicios o productos de software que me parezca que hacen algo increible.</li>
<li>Realiza una tabla con: empresa, qué hace?, cómo lo hace? por qué lo hace? cómo puedo contribuir? qué skills tengo que son transferibles? Qué roles de labores tienen estructurados? Qué personas son los líderes de equipos de roles en esa empresa? Qué retos tiene la empresa? Cómo puedo contribuir a solucionar esos retos?</li>
</ol>
<table><thead><tr><th>Empresa</th><th>Qué?</th><th>Cómo?</th><th>Por qué?</th><th>Cómo contribuir?</th><th>Qué skills son transferibles?</th><th>Nombres</th><th>Retos</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>IBM</td><td>Empresa de tecnología.</td><td>Realizan avances tecnológicos. Fabrica y comercializa hardware y software. Ofrece servicios de infraestructura, alojamiento de internet y consultoría.</td><td>Liderar un cambio innovador para mejorar los negocios,<br> la sociedad y la condición humana</td><td>Liderazgo, comunicación, desarrollo de productos de software</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>Infrastructure and Technology roles:</p>
<p><strong>Mainframe Technical Specialist</strong>
Code, maintain and scale our mainframe technology, which is critical for servers and applications that require high resiliency and agility.</p>
<p><strong>Storage Specialist</strong>
Design, analyze and manage the biggest and most complex storage solutions for our clients to drive performance and reliability.</p>
<p><strong>Site Reliability Engineer</strong>
Be in charge of combining software and systems engineering to build and run large-scale, massively distributed, fault-tolerant systems.</p>
<p>Security Roles:</p>
<p><strong>Security Specialist</strong>
Become a thought leader in DevSecOps practices and demonstrate hands-on expertise with security practices across the infrastructure and applications.</p>
<p>Software Engineering Roles:</p>
<p><strong>Software Engineer</strong>
Create complex software systems for some of the biggest clients in the world.</p>
<p><strong>Full Stack Developer</strong>
Integrate multiple systems with your code in an agile manner, every step of the way.</p>
<p><strong>DevOps Engineer</strong>
Work with our development and systems team in huge projects to automate, scale and deploy in an agile way.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="market-research" term="market-research"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I want?]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/what-I-want</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/what-I-want"/>
        <updated>2024-03-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What do I need to learn to know what I want?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do I need to learn to know what I want?</p>
<p>I want to learn about economy and how work transform societies.</p>
<p>I want to learn about organizations-startups and their structure.</p>
<p>I want to learn about what do I need in Mexico to create an organization.</p>
<p>I want to learn about Mexico's history.</p>
<p>I want to learn about authority.</p>
<p>I want to learn to build relations.</p>
<p>I want to learn what is market capitalization.</p>
<p>I want to learn what I do not know.</p>
<p>I want to know the leaders in Mexico's software industry.</p>
<ul>
<li>Create a table:
Industry : companies <!-- -->:leaders</li>
</ul>
<p>Research:
What is that industry why it is important?
What does the company and why it is important?
What leaders are in those companies, what do they do?
How can I contribute?</p>
<p>Where do I begin?</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="introspection" term="introspection"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What do I like?]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/self-exploration</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/self-exploration"/>
        <updated>2024-03-29T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[What do I like?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do I like?</p>
<p>I like to learn and integrate it into my worldview.</p>
<p>I like to find new methods to learn and make the integrative process of information into knowledge more holistic.</p>
<p>I like to understand the world around me.</p>
<p>I love to listen to music.</p>
<p>I love to think and explore herustically how all I am changes or reacts or function every moment.</p>
<p>I love to use my knoweldge and see how everythings fits together after reading about different topics.</p>
<p>I like to feel curiosity for what is in our planet, why it is here and how.</p>
<p>I love to feel energized and focused, so I love practicing 氣功.</p>
<p>I like to think of things that can't be seen, and how they impact the seen reality. I like to understand not obvious forces and mechanisms that power the movement of the reality.</p>
<p>I like to understand how the history impact the present and the civilization I'm living everyday.</p>
<p>I like to better understand why we do what we do as a society, and ask why are we focused on those things, are they really necessary or is just a very old force that still exits only for historical innertia?</p>
<p>I love my life but I do not accept everything as it is, I like to think are better ways to do this?</p>
<p>I deeply feel the pain and fear of others as I remember how it feel and how difficult it is to overcome it.</p>
<p>I like to think and feel that my life matters and it is relvant to our reality, to our world somehow, that I'm not only an irrelevant dissipative structure that lasts just a bit more than a tornado.</p>
<p>I like to feel the empowering sense that knowledge of our different sectors of civilization give me.</p>
<p>I like to learn how individuality and social distancing tendencies can be equilibrated with authority and social cohesion to balance my personality and be able to contribute but also to feel freedom to expose without extreme consequences my ideas.</p>
<p>I like to empower people around me with a mental state of freedom so they can feel less enslaved by current powerful states and at the same time direct them towards creative innovation. Not towards resentment, anger and ultimately criminal activity.</p>
<p>I like the balanced focus of oriental mindsets like buddism, taoism and confusionism.</p>
<p>I like to know whatever I am more and by knowing me more, know others. I like to increase my consciousness.</p>
<p>I love to still joy spontaneously like a child and enjoy for moments those deep feelings.</p>
<p>I love to find ever better approaches to solve my problems. There must be a way to do what I want to achieve!</p>
<p>I love to write what I think.</p>
<p>I like to develop methods although I then have difficulty following them!</p>
<p>I like to reciprocate and cooperate instead of compete, I think the biggest ever competition is oneself, that is the harder contrincant.</p>
<p>I like to inspire a long-term view to foster challenging each other collaboratively instead of short-term competition.</p>
<p>I like to understand that the best way to help others is giving the living example of what I believe.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="introspection" term="introspection"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Super short summary of The Worldly Philosophers]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas"/>
        <updated>2024-03-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I just read the book The Worldly Philosophers and to consolidate the ideas I wanted to write a summary here.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just read the book <strong>The Worldly Philosophers</strong> and to consolidate the ideas I wanted to write a summary here.</p>
<p>It is composed of many chapters that talk about different periods of the economic thinking focused on the personality and historical context of relevant economists, therefore it provides a more personal view behind the writters of economic theories.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="adam-smith">Adam Smith<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas#adam-smith" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Adam Smith" title="Direct link to Adam Smith">​</a></h2>
<p>is the first that introduced the idea of accumulated wealth and the effects over the production of goods that would have. We thought about the market supply and demand. For example, there are many bourgeoisie that were competing against each other for the market demand of certain products, they in consequence require more workers to produce more and be able to sell the products at a lower price, so to win a higher market share. That implies hiring more workers, nevertheless, given that others are competing for producing those products at lower prices too, they also want more workers, therefore, the labor market forces to a rising of salaries paid to the workers. That implies higher earnings for that social class. This would hinder the benefits of the bourgeoisie. Nevertheless, there is a limit to the number of goods that the population required, and bourgeois families could only buy that much for their needs. Therefore, that imposed a limit to demand of certain products, diminishing the demand for employees and therefore aliviating the pressure of rising salaries, because less work force was required to satisfy the current demand of the product. For Smith, overall, there was a net increment in the produced goods and total wealth in the system via accumulation of wealth.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="david-ricardo-and-malthus">David Ricardo and Malthus<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas#david-ricardo-and-malthus" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to David Ricardo and Malthus" title="Direct link to David Ricardo and Malthus">​</a></h2>
<p>were actively collaborated and discussed their views about economics. The main difference in their viewpoint compared to that one Adam Smith is that the accumulated wealth would be limited, there was a boundary to the development of the economic machine: It was reach because of the tendency of this social class of workers to increase its number with each rising of salary, therefore, balancing the laboral offer in the market and reducing in consequence the salary offered by the bourgeoisie. It was not even desirable for it would lead to a Tragedy of the Commons. More mouths to feed would imply more production of goods, but the land can only offer a limited amount of goods that can be extracted and satisfy the demand given a period of time. Thus, the economic growth was capped. (A net-zero game).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="john-stuart-mill">John Stuart Mill<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas#john-stuart-mill" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to John Stuart Mill" title="Direct link to John Stuart Mill">​</a></h2>
<p>was a well educated (he started to study greek at the age three and by 6 years old he already had read Plato's Dialogues and many other greek poets and writters) English economist, he also learnt latin very young. His father raise him with a strict and elite education, that had the negative impact of Mill having  crisis in his twenties where while other discovered that there could be beauty in intelectual work, Mill found that there could beauty in beauty. His main statement was the idea to separate production and distribution. He stated that the economic laws are only concerned with production, the distribution is completely separate from those laws. He said:</p>
<p>"The distribution of wealth depends on the laws and traditions of sociaty. The  rules that determine it are the opinions and feelings of those who govern the community; they are very different in distinct periods and distinct countries."</p>
<p>This reasoning has its flaws, distribution policies can have impacts over production. For example, if we tax 100% of the benefits, that will change where the money goes but also hinder the desire to produce more, therefore a distribution policy affects production! Also, as Marx pointed out, we cannot separate distribution from production completely, because how different sociaties organize their payment modes is a constitutive element of their production modes.</p>
<p>So the critics that Mill made concerning the freedom with which sociaties can reestructure their distribution of wealth has its limits. Nevertheless, its approach has importance, for the time, its ideas were considered a bit socialist (utopic socialism) but the concept of having the freedom to distribute wealth implied that government or other institutions could have an influence over the economic machinery and help to stabilize it, for example, via taxes on heritage and land rent. Also, in opposition to Ricardo and Malthus, he didn't considered that the economic growth would reach a maximum and then decrase as a consequence of an increase in population that exerted a negative impact over the benefitis of accumulated wealth. Instead, he believed that with education, people could be informed about the negative impacts of non-controled natality, so population could be controled so salaries would only increase and reach a maximum of wealth accumulation. Therefore, in Mills model, the economy would reach a high stationary phase where we would see an end to the capitalism and the economic process and start a phase or stage of beingn socialism, where humanity would focus his energy towards higher ideals like justice and freedom. At the present time we can think of Netherlands or the three scandinavias (Norway, Sweden, Denmark) and see the elevated level of social responsability.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="karl-marx-and-friedrich-engels">Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/economic-ideas#karl-marx-and-friedrich-engels" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels" title="Direct link to Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels">​</a></h2>
<p>had opposite different personalities. Marx was a German Scholar par excellence, slow, meticulous, exhaustively perfeccionist. Engels was happy, clever, energetic, communicative; he was fond of bourgeois pleasures and had a good palate for wine. Engels could quickly writte a treatise, Marx could get back over and over the same theme, endlessly. Engels talked multiple languages, Marx after twenty years of practice could only talk a horrible Teutonic English. Nevertheless, with all its weight, Marx was the most powerful mind of the two. Wherever Engels introduced amplitude, Marx contributed deepness.</p>
<p>Now, Marx was influenced by <em>Hegel</em> with its dialects theory, loosely speaking, Hegel's dialect says that change is permanent, every idea, every force helps to grow its opposite, then after a tension they both get fused into one unity, which in turn produced its own contradiction. History, was the expression of that flux of contradictory forces and ideas in conflict.</p>
<p>In the dialectical materlialism, the root principle to understand the history is that the production of goods, and its subsequent distribution, determines the order of the society. As we saw with the counterexample for Mills' complete separation of production and distribution, the distribution has an impact in the production too. Given that the dialectical materialism proposes that the architecture of social order (in hierarchical classes) is determined by the distribution of goods that in turn is determined by what is produced and how it is produced, we see that it is all connected. The distribution allocates resources to certain members of society (which in turn create a new social class) is dependent on the relation that those members have with what is produced and how it is produced. Depending on the nature of that relation is the position that the newly created social class will have in its society and will or not maintain. Therefore, given that what is produced is related to how it is produced, then new products can be created when new techiniques and technological and scientifical advancements happen. For example, a new kind of mineral can be extracted from deeper places if there is the technical capacity to do it and perhaps a new class of technical positions will be created, <strong>perhaps, the more disruptive the changes in production the odds of allowing a new social class to emerge are greater</strong>. Or an existing way of producing wheat using manual grinders will be improved using vapor grinders or electrial grinders, therefore if there was an existing guild of manual operators of grinders, with the development of electrical grinders, that guild could be displaced by others or even just disapear exerting pressure over other sectors of society to emerge.</p>
<p>Dialectical materialism does not say that ideas are not relevant, but it says that people originate their ideas based on the production and distribution and society order they happend to live in, and the influence of those ideas were primarely originated from those afromentioned aspects.</p>
<p>In times of Marx and Engels, the prediction or natural consequence of the structure and operation of capitalism indicated that it had to finish. Its base class (proletariat) was beign oppressed by the middle top class (bourgeoisie, aristocrats) who had the means of production, the proletariat only had its work force to produce.</p>
<p>The ideal model of capitalism that Marx proposed is one that does not have monopolies and that the value of a product is the accumulated work required to produce it (being the same view that David Ricardo had in that aspect). Then given those conditions (among others, for formal details read Das Kapital), an equitative relation between the value of the proletariat's work force and the value that should be paid for that is equal to the required subsistance of a proletarian, therefore if 6 hours of a man's work is required to pay for its subsistance requirements, then that is what is going to be paid by the capitalist. If that were the case, the capitalist would not get any accumulated gains, but they get it by what Marx called <strong>surplus value</strong>, that is, they hired the proletarian to work for 8-10 hours per day and only pay them what they need to subsist. Then the capitalist can sell the product and obtain an extra accumulated gain. This is possible given that they own and monopolize the production modes according to the legal ordering of private property. Given that all the capitalist try to get benefits but are all in competition. Given that to generate benefits they have to expand, to grow, they require more workers, therefore they also have to compete for the labor force. <strong>This rise salaries</strong>. This rising of salaries have a negative pressure over the benefits the owners of the production modes, therefore, the way they find the way out of that is to buy machines that can substitute the labor force of living workers. With these machines they can satisfy the market demands that pressures them to expand and also diminished the negative pressure of the rising salaries of the labor market on their benefits. This machines will throw out into the street to many workers, so accomplishing the same function that the increment in population had for Smith and Ricardo, i.e., to compete for jobs in the labor market. Now, this only solves one problem but generates other, given that the surplus is only obtainable via the living proletariat, (machines in Marx model cannot produce surplus, if you bought the machine at 10,000, then you can only get 10,000 of equivalent work force from the machine). And even then, the benefits would decrease given the reduced population adquisitive power, and reducing the demand for products. So the end result is a reduction in the rate of benefits, this produces a capitalist crisis, the smaller go into bankrupt. This is not the end, just one cycle, the bigger companies can adquire the machines at lower prices from the smaller bankrupting companies, the works are forced to accept devaluated salaries and then slowly, the surplus begins to appear again and with it big benefits. Each crisis exists to renovate the expansion capacity of the system.</p>
<p>This is the concept Marx called <strong>laws of movement</strong> of historical development. The process of depressions (economic recession) or crisis is the way the capitalism system works, it is not a flaw it is the way it functions.</p>
<p>But each crisis is worse than the last one, given that the bigger firms absorb the smaller ones and when these industrial monsters fall, the harm to the society is stronger. This would lead to the colapse of capitalism in the end.</p>
<p>It's great that Marx was able to predict economic cycles and consequences of those cycles over the long run of big industries, i.e., benefits tend to go down always. The only way to solve this is that the whole economy grows. This requires innovation, techonological progress. Companies are obliged to innovate. To sum up the model of dialectical materialism was great at predicting future process and events.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="economy" term="economy"/>
        <category label="history" term="history"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post-analysis of my last Software Project]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Last-stack-used</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Last-stack-used"/>
        <updated>2024-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="systems-design" term="systems-design"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is a question?]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/What-is-a-question</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/What-is-a-question"/>
        <updated>2024-03-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've come to realize that many of my concepts are highly intuitive and sometimes that works out well, but some other concepts are more complex and require a more elaborated mental model to support good conclusions.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've come to realize that many of my concepts are highly intuitive and sometimes that works out well, but some other concepts are more complex and require a more elaborated mental model to support good conclusions.</p>
<p>That is the case of questions. <strong>What is a question?</strong> I'll call this formulation WIQ</p>
<p>The first thing I realize when thinking about it is that is really difficult to analyze. First for the breadth and deepness of the ideas that come to my mind and second because my lake of known methodologies to approach endevours like this.</p>
<p>So I decide to go for it letting the flow of information in order to sink in my meaning of it. My intention is to create necessary conditions for the analysis but by no means I try to be exhaustive. It's beyond the current scope.</p>
<p>Second thing I note is my language limits (I recall Ludwig Wittgenstein aphorism: "Los límites de mi lenguaje son los límites de mi mundo" - I like the quote more in Spanish). When I noticed that WIQ is a self-referential formulation, then I inmediately fall into an ontological problem --&gt; Is there something I can compare to convey the idea of a self-referential formulation in the WIQ?</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="narratives">Narratives!!<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/What-is-a-question#narratives" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Narratives!!" title="Direct link to Narratives!!">​</a></h3>
<p>Perhaps is really hard to synthetize a comparable example for what I'm thinking and trying to communicate but narratives are great at transmitting highly dimensional-complex ideas!!</p>
<p>So, let's simplify it using a narrative because that is how I think I could undertand this situation better. Let's call a question X and an answer Y.</p>
<p>I'm something X whose existance is instanciated by a certain formulation of symbols (think of a symbol as a representation of some packet of information) that happend to be understood by other beings and generated by them in the first place. So I X, exist, conceptually but I'm only realized when formulated, and my essence is inferred by the realized instances. When I'm realized, many potential related questions coexist and are waiting to be formulated. Also, every time I'm formulated, infinite instances of something called Y, Y's are potentially created that are connected to my current formulation X' and intend to provide further information about X'.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="analysis">Analysis<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/What-is-a-question#analysis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Analysis" title="Direct link to Analysis">​</a></h3>
<p>I will not attempt to define what is X beyond saying that is a concept. I know that X exists because I create instances of it whose particular formulations are different from each other.</p>
<p>So I'll naively assume that I can know X via instances of it, and perhaps know better the nature of X exploring and analyzing instances of it that boils down to the realm of language. In different languages the particular symbols and syntactic rules change but let's focus on the two languages I know better. Let's forget in this approach about strict grammatical rules so to advance faster. More strict consideration will not invalidate the main arguments.</p>
<ul>
<li>In Spanish we formulate a question simply by preappending a ¿ and postappending a ? symbols to a sentence: ¿Es esto una pregunta? Respuesta: Sí</li>
<li>In English, let's simplify and formulate the question using only the symbol ? at the end. Is this a question? Answer: Yes</li>
</ul>
<p>So there we have it. Let's explore X and their related Y's via instances of it. One particular interesting instance of it is the WIQ formulation:</p>
<p><strong>What is a question?</strong></p>
<p>Now I think is more clear to see that is a self-referential question. A particular instance of the concept that is asking for its own meaning. Is like X being forced (via me writing the formulation) to say: What am I? (Let's not question whether X is capable of instanciating itself or is only subjected to the will of the users of it, us, humans formulating questions... I'll assume the latter).</p>
<p>Ok, so now I have a mental model on which I can think about questions, i.e. A concept I can explore and analyze via instances of it that I formulate. And this heuristic turns out to be sufficient to give an answer to the WIQ.</p>
<p><strong>What is a question?</strong> Answer: It is a concept whose realization is via instances I formulate and can be explored analyzing those instances, the product of the analysis is one or more instances of connected information intended to further inform about the formulated question, we call these later instances answers.</p>
<p>Great, now I have a better mental model to explore questions!!!</p>
<p>For example, will programming web applications be completely automated?</p>
<p>Thinking of a question as a concept whose nature can be examined via particular instances of it, we can see that this particular question is an instance of a concept whose nature can be examined via particular instances of formulated questions. In this case the instance is: <em>Will programming web applications be completely automated?</em></p>
<p>Each question instantiated can be related to multiple instance questions whose core concept is the same. Answering those questions will inform more about the nature of the concepts I'm trying to know about. I'm not saying that all knowledge should ultimately be a concept that abstracts an intuition or perception, but I'm saying that we can try to condensate information towards concepts via questions and see the whole process as an exploration of an unknown abstract idea.</p>
<p>Now with solid mental model to explore and analyze questions, and one that encourages us to think about answering question as an explorative and always expanding process, fearless of uncertainty instead of static answers.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="epistemology" term="epistemology"/>
        <category label="logic" term="logic"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is frontend automation near?]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Automating-frontend</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Automating-frontend"/>
        <updated>2024-03-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Will programming web applications be completely automated?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Will programming web applications be completely automated?</p>
<p>Though question to answer. So let's analyze it and try to formulate a good response. The idea that comes to my mind to start exploring the landscape consists in approaching a principled consideration in order to accumulate knowledge and arrive to an informed conclusion.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="historical-perspective">Historical perspective<a href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Automating-frontend#historical-perspective" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Historical perspective" title="Direct link to Historical perspective">​</a></h3>
<p>I'll just divide the pharagraphs for order of gradual evolution but was not a sequential process, all the advancements overlap in time, space, and industry axes.</p>
<p>First, Alan Turing, John Von Neumann, among others developed the foundational concepts of computing and programming. This was a highly manual job, deep <em>understanding</em> of computer's architecture was required.</p>
<p>Second, advances in early machine code for specific computer architectures. Team led by Maurice Wilkes developed the concept of microprogramming (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/1458043.1458047" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/1458043.1458047</a>). A method of implementing the behavior of machine instructions by means of more elementary operations, with direct correspondence with the functions of the physical components of the computer. The control of instructions was hardwired, composed of circuits that corresponds with execution of each instruction. This was difficult to <em>modify</em>, expensive to <em>design</em> but fast. Microprogrammed allowed for simpler designs, easier to modify but slower than hardwired control.</p>
<p>Assembly language emerged as a symbolic representation of machine code instructions. Instead of seeing addresses of instructions, programmers saw <em>abstract</em> symbols for instructions like read from memory, store into register rsp, etc.. This was easier to <em>understand</em>, <em>modify</em> and <em>maintain</em> as compared to raw machine code. Still, it was architecture instruction set dependent.</p>
<p>Then, the emergence of higher-level programming languages. With all the widely known advantages in <em>portability</em>, <em>understanding</em>, <em>maintainability</em>, among others. For what I know, assembly is possible only used for critical performance, systems programming, operating system development and embedded systems nowadays.</p>
<h3></h3>
<p>Now, is very general, because for what I know, changes happened gradually and at different phases in different industries and at different scales.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.imf.org/en/Publications/fandd/issues/2023/12/Scenario-Planning-for-an-AGI-future-Anton-korinek" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Great article for scenario planning for an AGI future</a></p>
<p>(<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06590" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Impact of AI on Developer Productivity: Evidence from GitHub Copilot </a>)</p>
<p><a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/57d002e01b631bc215df193b/t/6149b24140c1c1764ed27707/1632219713790/Susskind%2C+Handbook%2C+Updated%2C+21+September+2021+.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technological Unemployment</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="AI" term="AI"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mental methods to solve problems]]></title>
        <id>https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Solving-logical-problems</id>
        <link href="https://rogeliolozano.github.io/blog/Solving-logical-problems"/>
        <updated>2024-03-05T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[To start smoothly, I'll share ideas I consider important to keep in mind when hunting counterexamples and rapidly discard conjectures that will go nowhere when solving difficult logical-constructive problems. Almost anyone subconsciously does think in two or three of these approaches, but it is useful to have a reminder of these methods of thinking.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To start smoothly, I'll share ideas I consider important to keep in mind when hunting counterexamples and rapidly discard conjectures that will go nowhere when solving difficult logical-constructive problems. Almost anyone subconsciously does think in two or three of these approaches, but it is useful to have a reminder of these methods of thinking.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Think small – Start with small examples because they are easier to construct and reason about and allow you to grasp the fundamental ideas that are in the core structure of the problem.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Think exhaustively – There are usually only a small number of possible instances for the first non-trivial value of n. For example, there are only three distinct ways two intervals on the line can occur: as disjoint intervals, as overlapping intervals, and as properly nesting intervals, one within the other. All cases of three intervals can be systematically constructed by adding a third segment in each possible way to these three instances.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Hunt for the weakness – If a proposed algorithm is of the form “always take the biggest” (better known as the greedy algorithm), think about why that might prove to be the wrong thing to do.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Go for a tie – A devious way to break a greedy heuristic for example is to provide instances where everything is the same size. Suddenly the heuristic has nothing to base its decision on, and perhaps has the freedom to return something suboptimal as the answer.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Seek extremes – Many counter-examples are mixtures of huge and tiny, left and right, few and many, near and far. It is usually easier to verify or reason about extreme examples than more muddled ones.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Divide and conquer - A classical mental model to approach problems that can be divided into subproblems of smaller data size. The resulting structure after applying the method is usually a recursive tree where each node has the subproblem of smaller data size. One classical Example is MergeSort (with a runtime complexity of O(nlog(n)))</p>
</li>
</ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Rogelio Lozano</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/RogelioLozano</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="mental methods" term="mental methods"/>
    </entry>
</feed>